So today's דף *Daf* is 166 קס״ו *Kuf Samech Vav* and we
pick up with זהב בדינרין zahav bedinarin *Zahav bi-dinarin*. So we're dealing
with a ברייתא braisa *Beraita*. The משנה mishna *Mishnah* basically said
if you just say a phrase like if you have first of
all contradictory amounts, 100 זוז zuz. *Zuz* which is 20 סלעים *Sla'im*
or whatever, you go by the lesser amount. If you have the
words that are like
borrowed dollars in the amount of blank or סלעים *Sla'im*
in the amount of or סלעים *Sla'im* whatever without the number, then
you just assume two. Okay, so that was pretty clear. But then
the ברייתא *Beraita* quoted in the גמרא gemara *Gemara* said that if
you basically said, let's look at the first line of the ברייתא
*Beraita*, go back to the גמרא gemara *Gemara* on the bottom of
165b. We won't read the whole thing but the first line to
remind us: תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, *Tanu Rabanan*, אמר כסף kesef. *Amar
Kesef*, silver, אין פחות מדינר *Ein pachos mi-dinar*, that's one כסף *Kesef*,
one דינר dinar. *Dinar*. And the גמרא gemara *Gemara* discussed why you
interpret it as a coin and not as an ingot of silver.
כסף דינרין dinarin. ודינרין כסף *Kesef dinarin ve-dinarin kesef*, דינרי dinare *Dinarei*
of silver, so אין פחות משני דינרין *Ein pachos mi-shenei dinarin*, so
the minimum is two and you can't prove more and that's what
you assume it means. But then became the interesting הלכה halacha *Halacha*
which is כסף בדינרין *Kesef bi-dinarin*, silver in דינרין *Dinarin*, so אין
פחות משני דינרי זהב dinarei zahav כסף *Ein pachos mi-shenei dinarei zahav
kesef*. Then it's two דינרי dinare *Dinarei* worth of gold silver, silver
in the amount of two דינרי dinarei *Dinarei* worth of gold. Somehow
you interpret it in the opposite metal. And the same is true
if you say זהב zahav, בדינרי *Zahav bi-dinarei*, then
you mean gold in the amount of two דינרי dinarei *Dinarei* of
silver. So that's very bizarre. When you use the ב׳ *Bet*, you
interpret it to be in the amount of the other metal. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is now going to look at.
So let's start top of 166a. זהב בדינרין *Zahav bi-dinarin*, gold in
דינרין *Dinarin*, אין פחות משני דינרי כסף dinarei kesef? זהב *Ein pachos
mi-shenei dinarei kesef zahav*. So two דינרי dinarei *Dinarei* of silver worth
of gold. So why if we're dealing with gold, do you interpret
the word דינרי dinarei *Dinarei* to be silver? And the same you
could ask in the beginning of the ברייתא *Beraita*. ואימא דהבא פריכא
*Ve-eima dahava prichah*, first the question is, maybe it means like little
slivers of gold? Okay, maybe it means slivers of gold worth two
דינרי dinarei *Dinarei* of gold. And again the דינרי dinarei. *Dinarei* would
still remain within the gold context. ואימא דהבא פריכא בתרי דינרי dinarei
דהבא קאמר *Ve-eima dahava prichah bi-trei dinarei dahava kama*,
maybe it's sort of slivers of gold worth two דינרי dinarei *Dinarei*
of gold. אמר אביי Abaye. *Amar Abaye*, יד בעל השטר על התחתונה
yad baal hashtar al hatochtuna *Yad ba'al ha-shtar al ha-tachtona*. Yeah, but
the burden of proof is on the one who's trying to extract
the money, the person with the שטר Shtar *Shtar*. And since he
has the burden of proof, we're going to interpret the word בדינרי
*Bi-dinarei* to mean in דינרי dinarei *Dinarei* of silver, in a different
דינר dinar *Dinar*, in a lesser valuable דינר dinar *Dinar*. Okay, but
if the point is that we're always going to interpret it to
mean the smaller amount, then when somebody says דינרין *Dinarin*, somebody says
silver בדינרי *Bi-dinarei*, you should also say it means in silver דינרי
dinarei *Dinarei*, right? If the reason when you use gold in דינרי
*Dinarei* we mean gold in silver דינרי *Dinarei* because יד בעל השטר
על התחתונה yad baal hashtar al hatochtuna. *Yad ba'al ha-shtar al ha-tachtona*,
we're always going to interpret it as the lesser amount, so silver
in דינרי *Dinarei* should certainly mean silver in silver דינרי *Dinarei*. And
so we still don't understand it. So we'll read the parentheses because
that helps explicate the question the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is asking. רישא
דקתני כסף בדינרין אין פחות משני דינרי זהב dinarei zahav כסף אמאי
*Reisha de-katani kesef bi-dinarin ein pachos mi-shenei dinarei zahav kesef amai*? So
when you say silver in דינרין *Dinarin*, why do we say it
means silver worth two gold דינרי *Dinarei*? אימא כספא נסכא בתרי דינרי
כספא קאמר *Eima kaspa nascha bi-trei dinarei kaspa kama*. Say it means
like slivers or ingots of silver worth two דינרי *Dinarei* of silver.
If we're going to interpret the ambiguous in דינרי *Dinarei* to mean
silver because יד בעל השטר על התחתונה *Yad ba'al ha-shtar al ha-tachtona*,
we should certainly say that when you're starting with silver. אמר רב
אשי *Amar Rav Ashi*, רישא דקתני דינרי סיפא דקתני דינרין *Reisha de-katani
dinarei seifa de-katani dinarin*. Okay, so because of that question, which is
a really good question, רב אשי *Rav Ashi* is going to make
a distinction which seems to be somewhat artificial between saying דינרי *Dinarei*,
which means gold, and דינרין *Dinarin*, which means silver. Now the problem
is that דינרי *Dinarei* is סמיכות smichus, *Smichut*. Okay, so and that
to identify a difference between דינרי *Dinarei* and דינרין *Dinarin*, I mean
maybe in the Greek דינרי *Dinarei* is the plural, I think it
is, okay, but anyway, but if you're writing in, whatever, in Hebrew
or in Aramaic, so דינרי *Dinarei* and דינרין *Dinarin*, דינרי *Dinarei* say
דינרי זהב dinarei zahav *Dinarei Zahav*, right, it's סמיכות smichut *Smichut*, דינרין
*Dinarin* is just דינרין *Dinarin*. But he's making a distinction and he's
going to also presumably change the text of the ברייתא *Beraita* and
say the רישא *Reisha* that says כסף בדינרי kesef bedinare *Kesef bi-dinarei*,
because it says דינרי *Dinarei*, it means in the amount of gold
דינרי *Dinarei*. And the end that says זהב בדינרין *Zahav bi-dinarin* means
silver דינרין *Dinarin*. Okay, now where are we going to get this
distinction from? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומנא תימרא דשאני בין
דינרי לדינרין *U-mana teimra de-shani bein dinarei le-dinarin*, where do you see
to make that distinction? He says the רישא that says כסף בדינרי
because it says דינרי it means in the amount of gold דינרי
and the end that says זהב בדינרין means silver דינרין. Okay, now
where are we going to get this distinction from? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara. says ומנא תימא דשאני בין דינרי לדינרין. uminatema deshani bein
dinare ledinarin. Where do you see to make that distinction? דתניא detanya
we taught in a ברייתא האשה שהיו עליה ספק חמש לידות ספק
חמש זיבות ha'isha shehayu aleha safek chamesh leidot safek chamesh zivot a
woman who had five births and she doesn't know if all five
of them and they were all miscarriages, and she doesn't know if
maybe all five of them were real births, the child had already
been developing for 40 days, or whether it was before 40 days,
that determines whether or not it was considered to be an actual
לידה leida miscarriage or not, whether the child had been begun to
have been formed, and therefore, so she could be חייב chayav from
anywhere between zero to five קרבנות. korbanot. When a woman gives birth
or miscarries after 40 days after development of the fetus of conception,
she is obligated to bring a קרבן korban to make her טהור.
tahor. Okay, she has a חיוב קרבן chiyuv korban and the bringing
of the קרבן korban finishes the purification process, right? After she goes
to the מקוה mikvah and 40 days or 80 days depending on
whether it's a boy or a girl or so on. Okay, so
here, she doesn't know whether anywhere between zero and five of these
births were הלכה halacha births, or she had she bled three days
in a row. Now if a woman bleeds three days in a
row, she's not pregnant. If a woman bleeds three days in a
row, if it's during her normal menstrual period, she's a נדה, niddah,
even if she bleeds for a day she's a נדה. niddah. But
if it's during her non-menstrual period and she bleeds three days in
a row, she's a זבה. zavah. The difference is that a זבה
zavah is טמאה teme'ah for a longer period, she has to wait
for seven clean days. We somehow conflated the two in our contemporary
observance of הלכות נדה. Hilchos Niddah. And to finish the purification process
in addition to going to a מקוה, mikvah, she would actually bring
a קרבן. korban. So this woman
bled in multiple months, three days in a row, but her cycle's
all mixed up and she has no idea whether the bleeding occurred
during her נדה niddah period or during her זיבה zivah period. So
she is anywhere between a זבה zavah five times and zero times.
Okay, so how many קרבנות korbanot does she have to bring? Okay,
so yes.
If it's not a הלכה halacha. לידה, leida, if it's like what
if it was less than 40, if it was less than the
40-day period? Correct.
Correct, I mean if and she wouldn't be טמאה, teme'ah, well unless
there was bleeding, the bleeding might make her טמאה, teme'ah, but the
לידה leida would not make her טמאה. teme'ah. That is correct. Okay,
so ספק חמש לידות ספק חמש זיבות safek chamesh leidot safek chamesh
zivot מביאה קרבן אחד ואוכלת בזבחים. mavia korban echad ve'ochelet b'zvachim. Now,
the קרבן korban she's obligated to bring is two birds, one for
an עולה olah and one for a חטאת. chatas. So the rabbis
said, look,
we've got to let her bring one קרבן korban because if we
don't let her bring one קרבן, korban, this woman will never be
able to eat קרבנות korbanot in her life because until she brings,
you bring the קרבן korban at the end of the process, you
could touch things or whatever, and touch תרומה terumah or whatever, but
you can't eat קרבנות. korbanot. She's never fully טהור. tahor. So we
have to let her bring one קרבן. korban. The problem is what
do you mean let her? Maybe we should obligate her to bring
five קרבנות korbanot because maybe she's חייב chayav five? No, the problem
is עולות olot she can bring, she can bring as many עולות
olot as you want whether you're obligated or not. A חטאת chatas
you can't bring unless you're obligated. So there's a special, there's a
tradition that a woman who or a person who is like in
this case needs to bring a חטאת chatas not for a sin.
If you don't know whether you're obligated a חטאת chatas for a
sin, you don't bring it at all or you bring an אשם
תלוי asham talui depending on the circumstances. But a חטאת chatas that
is part of מחוסרי כפרה, mechusrei kapara, מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kapara means,
thank you, when the קרבן korban is necessary to finish the purification
process, that's the category of מחוסרי כפרה. mechusrei kapara. Okay, and in
those cases, if you don't bring it, what, are you going to
remain טמא tamei your whole life? So you bring it and it's
not eaten. Okay, you bring this חטאת העוף chatas ha'of and you
don't, it's not eaten as normally a חטאת chatas would be. It's
burnt, it's destroyed, and so on. So that's like, that's like a
real violation, like we have to allow that. We allow that, but
we want to minimize that because that's breaking the rules. Okay, I
mean again, not really breaking the rules because we have a rule
that we're allowed to break the rules. Okay, but the point is
it's breaking the standard rules. So therefore, we let her bring one
קרבן korban to make her טהור, tahor, but she does not, she's
not going to bring the
rest because maybe she's not חייב. chayav.
A full complement of one קרבן, korban, a
חטאת chatas and an עולה. olah. Okay, but she's not going to
bring the other four.
ואין השאר עליה חובה. ve'ein hash'ar aleha chova. She has no obligation
to bring the rest and not only no obligation, we wouldn't let
her. Okay, היו עליה חמש לידות ודאות חמש זיבות ודאות. hayu aleha
chamesh leidot vada'ot chamesh zivot vada'ot. Now let's say she definitely had
five different childbirths or miscarriages or whatever, or five different times she
was a זבה. zavah.
מביאה קרבן אחד ואוכלת בזבחים. mavia korban echad ve'ochelet b'zvachim. So then
one קרבן korban is enough to be, to make her able to
eat, right? Part of the חידוש chiddush of this משנה mishna is
that you don't say well since she became a זבה zavah five
times, she has to bring five קרבנות korbanot in order before she
becomes טהורה. tehorah. And the way the גמרא Gemara says one קרבן
korban is enough to make her טהורה tehorah is the גמרא Gemara
says imagine that, let's say a woman was a נדה niddah five
times. How many times would she have to go to the מקוה
mikvah before she became טהורה? tehorah? One. Okay. Imagine
somebody touched a נבלה. nevelah. five different נבילות neveilas on five different
days. How many times would they have to go to the מקוה
mikvah to become טהור? tahor? Once. So an act that seeing this
קרבן korban not as a personal obligation to bring a קרבן, korban,
but as a ritual that creates טהרה, tahara, the גמרא Gemara. assumes
that even if you are טמא tamei multiple times within the same
category, one קרבן korban achieves the טהרה tahara process. Okay, after she's
been to the מקוה mikvah whatever. Okay, so one קרבן korban suffices
to make her טהורה, tehora, והשאר עליה חובה, vehashe'ar ala chova,
and the rest is an obligation like anybody who's חייב chayav to
bring a קרבן korban and bring it when you're able. Okay, so
that was all very fascinating, what that has to do with דינרים
dinarim and דינרי we haven't seen yet. מעשה, Maise, עמדו קינים בירושלים
בדינרי זהב. amdu kinim birushalayim bedinarei zahav. Ah,
now we're getting the word דינר. dinar. There was a so in
ירושלים Yerushalayim there was an event that happened that a קן, kan,
a קן kan is two birds, a you know, which would be
brought as an עולה olah and a חטאת. chatas. So they were
going for דינרי of זהב, let's assume means two דינרי because okay
again, the minimum is two. Anyway, they were extremely expensive, right? There
was a high demand, so you know, maybe I don't know if
there was a low supply or maybe the suppliers made a little
bit of a monopoly, not a monopoly, what's that called? Collusion, okay,
and therefore they were going at extremely exorbitant prices. So אמר רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, says רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, המעון הזה, hamaon hazeh,
this dwelling place, meaning he's took an oath in the name of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, אם אלין הלילה, im alin halaila,
I will not go to sleep tonight, עד שיהיו בדינרים, ad sheyihu
bedinarim, until the
until the birds they go down from worth דינרי זהב to דינרים.
dinarim. So now you see דינרים dinarim means כסף. Okay, now of
course the problem is דינרי is סמיכות, smichut. I'll get back to
that but let's finish this story. Okay, so he said I'm going
to get them to go down from gold דינרי to silver דינרי.
What did he do? נכנס לבית הדין ולימד, Nichnas leveis hadin velimed,
he went into the בית דין beis din and he taught the
following הלכה. halacha האישה שהיו עליה חמש לידות ודאי חמש זיבות ודאי
מביאה קרבן אחד ואוכלת בזבחים ואין השאר עליה חובה. Haisha shehayu aleha
chamesh leidot vadai chamesh zivot vadai, mevia korban echad veocheles bizvachim, veein
hashear ala chova.
One קרבן korban is enough and she doesn't have to bring the
rest. Now I'm going to get back to unpack all this but
let's just finish the story. Okay, so now all these women that
had all these sacrifices, these built-up obligations, because they had you know
had many maybe a lot of a lot of miscarriages, a lot
of births and they you know finally at the end of a
few years came to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, instead of having to bring ten
קרבנות, korbanos, they only had to now bring one קרבן. korban. So
the price plummeted. Okay, ועמדו קינים בו ביום ברבעתים. veamdu kinim bo
bayom beriva'tayim.
And the קינים kinim rather than being being going for a דינר
dinar, of gold or a דינר dinar. of silver, went for a
רבע, reva, a רבע reva is a quarter of a דינר. dinar.
Okay, so he really crashed the price you know, he cut down
even lower of a silver דינר, dinar even lower than he had
been going for.
Quarter of a silver דינר.
dinar. Quarter of a silver דינר. So even less and I think
a silver דינר is a 25th of a gold דינר. So he
said he was going to get it down to a 25th of
the original value if I'm right, somebody can check that. Anyway, it
was even a quarter, his his strategy made it work for even
a quarter of the value of what he was going for. Okay,
so very successful. Now let's talk about a few things about, right,
let's talk about a few things and then we'll get back to
the דינרים dinarim and the דינרי but first let's talk about one
or two things about this actual story itself. So first of all
the question is like what's he doing? He's פסקן paskening a wrong
הלכה halacha to manipulate the prices? So you know of course the
גמרא Gemara says no no no, of course this was the הלכה
halacha he believed in, you know, maybe he was not he was
not professing it, you know, maybe in you know maybe people you
know were bringing a קרבן korban and that was okay and maybe
or maybe they were following another more stricter פסק psak and he
wasn't going to make a point of pushing through his more lenient
פסק, psak, but because of this sort of social need, he was
either saying like you don't have to be so מחמיר, machmir, you
know, you don't have to do this like tech if you want
to bring it געזונטהייט gezuntheit but you're not obligated to, right, or
he basically said no, I'm going to really get behind this פסק
psak I believe in that I haven't been pushing until now, but
we really do have to push it. And it's very interesting the
way in which rabbis, you know at different stages sometimes use their
either פסק psak or תקנה takana muscle in order to, you know,
protect the people so that the religious obligations would not lead to
runaway prices.
I think there was a time recently where there was some group
some group of rabbis basically they were saying that people can't spend
more than a certain amount on a לולב lulav and an אתרוג.
esrog. But the most famous examples have to do with sumptuary laws.
Yes sumptuary is a little different because that's just saying don't overspend
for for expense on a wedding as opposed to like you know
the people who are manipulating the prices of ritual objects, you know,
so there was anyway, so there was the most common one was
about which I think occurred over you know decades if not centuries,
was around buying fish for שבת, Shabbos, that you know that it
was obviously this very strong מנהג minhag that you have fish on
שבת Shabbos and the fishmongers were jacking up the prices. So basically
you know a lot of the rabbis in the various... generations, various
times, basically said it's אסור *assur* to buy fish for שבת *Shabbos*
until the prices went back down. So, you know, but that's a
more of like a תקנה *takkanah*, right? I mean it's maybe it's
more saying that you have to forgo, you know, a certain קיום
*kiyum*, nobody's actually you know that you know, it's a little different
than like this which is like a real פסק הלכה *psak halacha*
type of an issue.
The issue as opposed to the fish is exactly, exactly.
So anyway, but one way of saying is, this is real פסק
*psak*, he just wasn't pushing it until now.
Meaning he actually disagreed with everyone else. What? Meaning he actually disagreed
with everyone else.
Or, yeah, he disagreed with what the accepted or the perceived פסק
*psak* was and he was pushing it through here. You have this
elsewhere, you have it in פסחים *Pesachim* where שמואל *Shmuel* basically says,
you know, teaches about whether you have to כשר *kasher* certain you
know of vessels after פסח *Pesach* or whatever because people were jacking
up the prices of vessels after פסח *Pesach*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* never assumes that they're teaching something which they really don't believe
in, but they're like publicizing something they otherwise would not have publicized
and you have a couple of instances about this. Now, the question
though still is, that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks is, we've never seen
this position yet, that, you know, if you have five לידות *leidot*,
you bring one קרבן *korban* and you don't have the rest as
an obligation. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says if you look at all
the other evidence and all the other גמרות *Gemaros*, nobody ever says
that. If you had five separate לידות *leidot*, of course you're obligated
to bring five. So he says that the actual גרסא *girsa* is,
השאר לחובה *hashar lechova*, not אין השאר לחובה *ein hashar lechova*. That
what they've actually been פסקן *paskening* beforehand was that you had to
basically bring all five before you were טהורה *tehorah*, okay? And you
know, and then he said he corrected it to what we had
been teaching earlier, but the difference is, okay, but it's one thing
to say eventually I'll get around to bringing my other קרבנות *korbanot*,
but the more urgent thing is that I bring one. Okay, so
there, even though he did not exempt these women from the ultimate
need to bring however many קרבנות *korbanot* they had to bring, by
removing the urgency and saying all you have to do right now
is one, the rest you can worry about, you know, worry about
later, worry about when you find a good time to buy the
birds and they're not going at a high price or whatever, so
by removing the urgency, that affected, you know, had a serious impact
on the prices in the markets. So there's an interesting question about
which הלכה *halacha* he was teaching. Yes, Rabbi Idow?
Related to the idea of
contemporarily where the idea of
of revisiting minority opinions from generations past to address social issues or
other...
Oh, yeah, sort of like being סומך על דעת יחיד בשעת הדחק
*somech al da'at yachid besha'at hadachak*, but seeing the שעת הדחק *sha'at
hadachak*, you know, sort of being, right, like to address serious economic
social types of concerns. Yeah, absolutely, absolutely. And you know, definitely people
that have historically more tried to, you know, promote the the
explicit or at least conscious, you know, use of of values or
policy in the process of פסק *psak*, like have really made reference
to these types of גמרות *Gemaros*, like if you look at like
Eliezer Berkovits's writings or, you know, others, you know, he's I mean
like they have sections where they say look at all here all
these places where the rabbis were very consciously, you know, factoring in
policy into their פסק הלכה *psak halacha* considerations. You know, the ironic
thing is that everybody factors in policy, the question is just which
policy, the liberal policies or the conservative policies, you know, so anyway,
that's a separate conversation. But yes. Now, let's get back to the
דינרים dinarim. ודינרי *dinarim u-dinarei*. So the question is, what type of
a proof is this? דינרי זהב *dinarei zahav* is סמיכות smichut, *smichut*,
it's not that the word דינרי *dinarei* by itself means זהב *zahav*.
Actually you could prove the
opposite. Had it just said דינרי *dinarei*, if דינרי *dinarei* by itself
meant זהב *zahav*, they would have just said דינרי *dinarei*, they wouldn't
have said דינרי זהב *dinarei zahav*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* asks that
question, and I just want to read one line of תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* just so you see that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*'s discussion of grammar
for the grammarians among us. So he says, אמר רב אשי רישא
דכתיב דינרי *Amar Rav Ashi reisha de-chtiv dinarei*. Okay, wait is that
the one? No, the next one. לפי הספרים *lefi ha-sfarim*, the next
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, שגורסים עד שיהיו בדינרים ולא גרסינן בדינר של כסף
לא ידענא היכי פשיט מיניה דדינרי של זהב ודינרים של כסף *she-gorsim
ad she-yihyu bi-dinarim ve-lo garsinan be-dinar shel kesef lo yadana heichi pashit
minei de-dinarei shel zahav ve-dinarim shel kesef*. I don't understand what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is learning out here. דילמא האי דקאמר דינרי של
זהב גבי זהב *Dilma hai de-ka'amar dinarei shel zahav gabei zahav*, why
does it say דינרי *dinarei* with the זהב *zahav*? מחמת הדביקות *machmat
ha-devikut*, which is what we call סמיכות smichut *smichut*. Okay, because of
the way in which the words are, you know, not juxtaposed, but
linked, that it's like possessive. דינרים dinarim *dinarim* of זהב *zahav* is
דינרי *dinarei*. אבל בלא דביקות יאמר לעולם דינרים ולא דינרי סתם *Aval
belo devikut yomar le-olam dinarim velo dinarei stam*. Maybe דינר *dinar*, דינרים
*dinarim*, whatever all mean silver, and if you wanted to mean זהב
*zahav*, you have to put it a modifier, דינרים של dinarim shel.
זהב *dinarim shel zahav*, דינרי זהב *dinarei zahav*, etc. דינרי *dinarei* still
by itself would not mean gold. Where do you get the idea
that דינרי *dinarei* by itself means gold? So in order to answer
this, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* switches the גרסא *girsa* so that both the
רישא *reisha* and the סיפא *seifa* have modifiers. That the רישא *reisha*
says בדינרי דינרי זהב *be-dinarei dinarei zahav*, and then it says עד
שיעמדו *ad she-ya'amdu*, I'm not gonna go to sleep, עד שיעמדו בדינרים
של כסף *ad she-ya'amdu bi-dinarim shel kesef*.
So the question is, I don't understand, if both of them need
a modifier, neither of them means סתם, and both of them means
a modifier, why here did you say סמיכות דינרי זהב and here
when you're talking about silver you say דינרים של כסף? dinarim shel
kesef? Why not say דינרי כסף? So that's the דיוק. diyuk. It's
a... now it's a very small point. The fact that here you
say דינרי זהב and here you say דינרים של כסף dinarim shel
kesef means that when we're going to be talking about gold we're
going to use the word דינרי and when we're talking about silver
we're going to use the word דינרים. Aren't you persuaded? Okay.
Now we're going to move on. What?
No, you... they're both סמיכות. In one you're going to say דינרי
and the other you're going to say דינרים של. dinarim shel Right.
דינרים של isn't הלכתית, halachically, isn't grammatically סמיכות, right?
סמיכות is where the... yeah, yes, but they both have modifiers, okay,
but the fact that we chose this way to express the modifier
by gold and this way by silver means that the word דינרי
is going to be defaulted to mean gold and דינרים defaulted to
mean silver. I don't know what to say. We're going to move
on. There's not too much to say about that. Okay. Next point.
Alright, let's now start on the עמוד ב. amud beis. I know.
Okay.
כסף ומלוה. kesef umalveh. Now, what happens if the משנה mishna goes
on to say if you have a contradiction of the top and
the bottom, okay? So the top says, you know, 100, and the
bottom says 200. So you go by the bottom, okay? The bottom
is seen as to be the one that is, you know, is
authoritative if there's a contradiction. Why it doesn't spell it out, I
really don't know why, maybe it's because it's near the signature of
the witnesses. You don't need the bottom, you could just say it
once and then you'll go by the once, but if you have
it twice, it goes by the bottom. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so then why do you bother saying the... doing having the top
one, right? If you're really just going to go by one and
it's going to be the bottom, why even say the one at
the top at all? To which the משנה mishna answers, not that
this... the top will win out if there's a conflict, but let's
say it's... there's, you know, something got erased. Let's say the bottom
said like this. Okay? You know, that digit got erased. So because
you wrote it twice, it's sort of like a backup copy. You
know? So if you... you know, so because it... they didn't have
backup copies, but because it appears twice within the document, if in
this line a key thing is missing, you can fill it in
from the top. That's what the משנה Mishna said, okay? כדי שאם
נמחק אות אחת, kedai sheim nimchak os achas, if one letter gets
erased, you can fill it in from the top. So let's take
a look at the
גמרא. Gemara, תנו רבנן, our Rabbis taught. ילמי תחתון מן העליון באות
אחת, yilmi tachton min haelyon beos achas, you can learn the bottom
from the top with... to fill in one letter, אבל לא בשתי
אותיות, aval lo bishtei osiyos, but not to fill in two letters.
Now, וכגון, uchegon, now I gave the issue about in terms of
the amount. The גמרא Gemara is going to give the issue in
terms of the person. Who's owed the money? So it says, David
owes
חנן מחנני. Chanan meChanani. So on the bottom it's... so it says
here,
David borrowed
100 dollars from
חנני. Chanani. And here it says, David borrowed 100 dollars from
חנן Chanan and some letter got... and there was some letter that
got erased. Was it a... נון סופית? nun sofis? Doesn't seem to
be. It seems like we're dealing with a question of erasure, okay?
But who knows, maybe that was חנניה Chananya or maybe that was,
I don't know, חננאל Chananel or something like that. So we can
figure out that that means חנני Chanani at the... at the bottom.
We can figure that out, and now we know that that's the
one you owe the money to. Okay. אות אחת. Os achas. That's
אות אחת. os achas. וענן מענני. veAnan meAnani. So the גמרא Gemara
says, מאי שנא שתי אותיות דלא? mai shena shtei osiyos dlo? Now,
what about if this was חננאל? Chananel? You can't learn it, you
can't learn it out, even though clearly this has two letters erased.
So the question is like, first of all, let's just pause for
a moment. Well, let's read the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara is
going to ask why not, but the גמרא Gemara answer is not
going to be so clear. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: מאי שנא שתי אותיות דלא, mai shena shtei osiyos dlo, why
can you not learn out two letters? דילמא מצטרמי שאין בהן ארבע
אותיות והוה ליה פלגא דשמא, dilma mitrami sheein bahen arba osiyos vehavei
lei palga deshma, because maybe you'll have a four-letter name, and by
learning out two of the letters, you're going to be like the
majority of the name is going to be filled in, and that's
like, you know, that's not considered just like, you know, filling in
a gap, that's like changing what the document is saying somehow. It's
doing too radical of a read. So the גמרא Gemara says, if
that's true, אי הכי אות אחת נמי, ei hachi os achas nami,
you shouldn't be allowed to use one letter. דילמא מצטרמי שאין בהן
שתי אותיות והוה ליה פלגא דשמא, dilma mitrami sheein bahen shtei osiyos
vehavei lei palga deshma, maybe you'll have a two-letter
word and you'll learn out half of the word from the top
of the document.
Oh, come on, what name only has two letters?
Thank you, Dov. אלא, Ela, אלא, ela, שתי... shtei...
he's funny, his name, Dov.
אלא, Ela, you spell דב Dov without a ו? vov?
That's a very interesting question. In the תנ"ך, Tanakh, I think it's
without a ו. vov. I signed mine without a ו. Vav. Okay
anyway, אלא Ela says the גמרא, Gemara אלא
שתי אותיות היינו טעמא Ela shtei otiot hainu taama what here's the
reason two letters we don't write off on, דלמא משתמש בין שלוש
אותיות והוי להו רובא דשמא. Dilma mishtamesh bein shalosh otiot vehavei lehu
ruba deshmo. Because we're afraid you'll have a three-letter word and it'll
be the majority of a name. Now it's still not clear so
I don't know why you allow one letter, maybe you'll have a
two-letter word. But I guess
the point is
is
that anything more than the smallest name of two letters, you know,
most you know, I don't know, three let- wait what?
One isn't the majority of two.
Oh right, one is just half of two. Yeah, that's a good
point, thanks, right, that's the answer. Okay so we're afraid that the
majority of a name you could fill in, but but more than
the majority, I mean excuse me one more time, half of a
name you could supplement but the majority of a name you cannot.
Thank you, that's a good point.
Now isn't the majority? פלגא Palga is always half, right?
Yeah.
דלמא משתמש בין שלוש אותיות והוי להו רובא דשמא. Dilma mishtamesh bein
shalosh otiot vehavei lehu ruba deshmo. All right now now the question
is here okay but who the heck cares? Who the heck cares
if it's רובא דשמא Ruba deshmo or not רובא דשמא? Ruba deshmo?
First of all there's a couple of questions. First of all תוספות
Tosafos says I don't understand, so in a case where it wasn't
רובא דשמא, Ruba deshmo, right, you're going to say that this poor
guy חננאל Chananel can't collect his שטר Shtar. because we're not going
to fill it in because we're going to have to protect it
in case when it's a three-letter word? Like how's that fair to
this guy? What type of- is this some גזירה? Gezeira? Like that's,
you know, question number one. Even in the case where you don't
want to, why are you making this absolute rule, right? And it's
so unfair to the person who really owns this שטר. Shtar That's
like question number two- תוספות Tosafos doesn't have a good answer to
that, he just leaves that as a question, he says I don't
understand that at all. Okay that's point number one. Point number two
though is why can't you even if it was you know you
know a- here we'll do it like this- even if let's say
it was a word here this was יעל Yael and this was
י Yud blank blank. So what would be the big deal? Like
why not fill it in? Okay so the רשב״ם Rashbam says that
well we're really not talking that something got erased we're really talking
about the fact that it didn't get written at all and that
the סופר Sofer made- like so I mean maybe again this wouldn't
be a good example because a י Yud is not somebody's name.
But if you go back to this example חננאל Chananel or something
and this was חנן Chanan so he says we're not going to
assume that the סופר Sofer forgot to write two letters, okay, one
letter he could forget to write, two letters he won't. And therefore
we're going to assume that he really meant to say חנן. Chanan.
And therefore we'll find some guy by the name of חנן. Chanan.
Now the problem with saying that is number one it should have
been a נון סופית. Nun Sofit. Number two the משנה Mishna is
talking about a concern of erasures not about forgetting to have written,
right? And number three is sometimes that won't be a name at
all. In the example I gave if this says like יעל Yael
and this is י Yud or whatever it's not there's nobody by
the name י Yud that is the person who's owed the money,
right? So clearly like you know why shouldn't we? That's the more
logical thing to do. So תוספות Tosafos says it is not a
case of the סופר Sofer forgetting and saying he wouldn't have forgot
two letters so obviously there must be a guy by the name
י. Yud. That's not the case. Okay the case in the משנה
Mishnah clearly is that there's an erasure and we don't know what
was written. Okay and תוספות Tosafot just basically says I mean that's
clearly the פשט Pshat but תוספות just basically leaves it as a
quest- somehow if this is what the שטר Shtar means, you know,
then the שטר shtar? isn't clearly testifying to something, you can't like
fill in an essential part of the עדות Edut is almost what
it is saying. You know if you think about the fact like
two עדים Edim came and testified, right? So they sort of said
like you know the- maybe this is a very loose comparison but
I'll give it anyway. You know the גמרא Gemara says let's say
two עדים Edim were running after- there a guy was running after
somebody with like a knife, a murder weapon, right? And he was
running- I'm going to kill him I'm going to kill him I'm
going to kill him, and he runs into a house and the
עדים Edim are running after him and they walk in a second
after him and there he is he's holding the knife over the
guy with blood dripping from it and the guy's got a stab
wound in his heart, they can't testify that he committed murder because
they didn't actually see the act. You can't like fill in the
gaps by עדות. Edut. You have to see things. Now there are
times you can fill in the gaps like sometimes we say הן
הן עדי ייחוד הן הן עדי ביאה, Hen hen edei yichud hen
hen edei biya, like if a couple that you sort of assume
because of their relationship will most likely be having sex and then
they go into private and the witnesses see them go private you
could assume that's like they saw them having but sex but for
the most part we don't fill in the gaps. עדות Edut you
have to sort of see directly. So תוספות isn't saying this but
my my read is is now if you looked at the whole
thing as עדות Edut which you should, then you're not filling in
gaps here the עדים Edim actually said this, they said the part
at the top, the part at the bottom they were mumbling, you
know if you want to use that analogy, so you fill in
the mumbling from the thing they said explicitly. So I still don't
really know the answer. But if you look at this as the
only real עדות Edut then you could say they're not explicitly testifying
to who is owed the money and you can't fill in an
essential part of their testimony from circumstantial evidence okay even though obviously
this should be informing it. That's a way of understanding this. Like
I said, it's not really great, because why not say they're testifying
to the thing on the top as well? But anyway, somehow even
though it's erased and it's not this thing that the סופר sofer
would have forgot, clearly there was a name here and it got
erased, and the name wasn't somebody by the name י. Yud. Nevertheless,
the הלכה is you cannot fill in more than a one-letter gap.
That's getting, you know, that's too much of what isn't being said.
So that's basically, clearly seems to be what the גמרא says. Again,
it still doesn't explain, you know, this issue about when it's a
longer word, but the point is anything that is a significant fill-in—maybe
the way to read the גמרא is not גזירה, gezeira, but since
in some times two letters is a significant fill-in, we always consider
a two-letter filling-in of a gap as being too significant of, you
know, of saying something, you know, it's not a trivial sort of
type of filling in.
And it's being רובא דשמא? ruba d'shma?
You'd have to
say even if it's
a nine-letter word, it's not רובא דשמא, ruba d'shma, but since in
some contexts two letters is substantial, something like that. It's a very
hard גמרא to understand. The last point I'll say is: What do
you do with this שטר? shtar. Okay, so the רשב"ם Rashbam would
say in the case where it said חנן Chanan up here and
חנן Chanan down here, the רשב"ם Rashbam says you find some guy
by the name of חנן Chanan and you give him the שטר.
shtar. Okay, I mean, let's say it was חנן בן יעקב Chanan
ben Yaakov and this said חנן בן יעקב. Chanan ben Yaakov. You'd
find some guy by the name of חנן בן יעקב Chanan ben
Yaakov and you'd give him the שטר. shtar תוספות says that's crazy.
תוספות says the שטר shtar. just is not used. Like it's just,
it's unusable, but you don't give it to somebody whose name happens
to work out here, you know, when it clearly seems that it's
not like the amounts are contradicting. Like if this down here said,
you know, שמעון בן יעקב Shimon ben Yaakov
and this down here said ראובן בן יעקב, Reuven ben Yaakov, then
you'd give it to ראובן. Reuven. That's when we say the bottom
trumps the top. The same way if this has a hundred and
this has two hundred, you make it two hundred. But if this
clearly is like a partial name and it's been erased or the
סופר sofer forgot some letters, תוספות says you just would void the
שטר. shtar Yes.
It sounds like you're interpreting this as the second clause is a
repeat of the first part. Right. But what if it's possible that
it's a second clause and so the question is not about the
first clause which is not erased and might be valid, but the
second clause which is not clear who it's for and so it
can't be used?
It could be, meaning the language of the משנה Mishnah and תוספות
at one point suggests like maybe they've given emphasis. Maybe the first
one talks about how much is borrowed, how much is owed, and
then if you think about like a כתובה, kesubah, at a certain
point it mentions like נכסים דאית להון אחריות דלית להון אחריות. nechasim
d'is lehon achrayus d'lis lehon achrayus. So the second part more is
explicit about the liens. So there's two aspects of the same thing,
but one about the loan and one about the liens. Or you
could have said that like, I don't know, maybe the second one
isn't even talking, is only indirectly talking about this, but we're filling
in a gap based on, you know, clearly, well, presumably it's the
same actor referred to up here as the actor referred to down
here, but they're talking about the same...
here's a hypothetical: the שטר shtar says I borrowed a hundred dollars
from Joe and I borrowed a hundred dollars from David. Aha.
But or like חנן Chanan borrowed a hundred dollars from Joe and
חנניה Chananya borrowed a hundred dollars from David.
Right. So maybe it has two separate עדויות eduyot and that's our
concern.
Right, so the clause that's not erased might still be valid.
Right, that could
be. Right, so that would limit it to contexts where it doesn't
seem to be echoing the top, and in contexts where it seems
to be echoing the top we should be more prepared to fill
it in, right. Yeah.
And maybe is
there this...
is this like the top and the bottom section of a כתובה?
kesubah? Similar. I mean, the top of the כתובה kesubah doesn't mention
the money twice. It first says the wedding and then it mentions
the money.
Those are the principal and
the extras.
Yeah, there's no real חזרת עניינים chazaras inyanim so much at the
bottom of the כתובה. kesubah. I mean, it mentions, first it says
they got married, what...
so let's say, you know, the חתן choson obligates himself to a
hundred dollars, right, right, and also, you know, חנניה Chananya obligates himself
to another two hundred.
Right. I understand, I understand. So it's possible. But again, the משנה
Mishnah says if you go by the bottom, why even bother writing
the top? So the fact that the משנה says why bother writing
the top makes it sound very much that we're dealing with an
echoing of what was said at the top. So it's... if we
really are dealing with an echoing, it's hard to understand why we
shouldn't be able to fill in two letters. I suggest... I said
what I could suggest as a way of thinking about it. Yeah.
Is there any parallel between the wills when we say that we
go by the last...
oh, will and testament? No, not really. That's a question about like
when we think that he has the right to retract, whereas here
there's a question about contradicting and what, you know, which is going
to dictate.
I mean, I see the will would be consistent in itself, it's
just...
exactly, right. I see a loose parallel, but I don't think it's
the same logic. Okay, so let's... Okay, so let's just do a
little bit more.
אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa פשיטא לי peshita li obvious to
me ספל מלמעלה וקפל מלמטה safal milmala vekafal milmata if it says
the word ספל safal on the top and קפל kafal at the
bottom. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, you know, some say that these
are just made-up words, but they're just talking about like types of
ways in which there are differences. But if you want to say
it means something, תוספות first suggests ספל safal means סף פלגי, saf
palgi, sixty half-shekel or whatever it is, half-zuz. And קפל kafal means
קוף פלגי, kof palgi, a hundred half-shekel. Okay, the רשב"ם Rashbam says
ספל safal means, what's a ספל? safal? A ספל safal is like
a
ספל, sefel, a cup, a cup.
Right, right.
And קפל kafal he says maybe means like מכפלא, mikfela, תפלא, tefela,
maybe means like a טלית. tallit. So what did he borrow? If
it says that somebody borrowed something, did he borrow a cup or
did he borrow a טלית? tallit? Okay, so הכל הולך אחר
התחתון. hakol holech achar hatachton. So again, if it's like a hundred
and two hundred, the bottom line dictates. Okay, now בעי
רב פפא. baei Rav Papa. Now that's פשיטא peshita for רב פפא,
Rav Papa, but here's his question: קפל מלמעלה וספל מלמטה. kafal milmala
vesafal milmata.
So it says קפל kafal above and ספל safal below. מאי? mai?
What do you say? Do you say that it's a ספל safal
and it's a טלית tallit or whatever, it's sixty half-shekels as opposed
to a hundred half-shekels? Or here's another possibility: מי חיישינן לזבוב או
לא? mi chashinan lezvuv o lo? תיקו. teiku.
Maybe the bottom actually said קפל, kafal, but as the ink was
drying, here it said קפל, kafal, and as the ink was drying,
a fly came and sat on this part, and I don't know,
it would have to have sat on this part and like moved
around a little and smudged it a little, okay, and turned it
into ספל. safal. Okay, and in that way, it should really be
ספל safal and not קפל. kafal. So we don't know, you know,
we don't know if this is a case of נמחק nimchak and
we would go by the top, or if this is a case
of a contradiction and we go by the bottom. So the גמרא
says תיקו, teiku, and the guy I guess can't collect either or
collects the lesser of the two or something. I don't know. Okay,
so ההוא דהוה כתיב ביה שית מאה וזוזא. hahu dehavah ketiv bei
shis mea vezuza.
There was a שטר shtar, that had written in it, you know,
David here borrowed from me six hundred and a זוז. zuz So
six hundred what? Okay, שלחה רב שרביא קמיה דאביי. shalchah Rav Sharvaya
kamey deAbaye. רב
שרביא Rav Sharvaya sent this to אביי. How are you going to
interpret the six hundred? שית מאה איסטרי וזוזא, shis mea istari vezuza,
six
hundred איסטרי. istari. Now, just to confuse you all, there's two types
as you might remember. There's מנא צורי mana tzori and מדינה, medina,
and
they're, one is eight times the other. So an איסטרי istari could
be a half זוז zuz or it could be four זוזא. zuza.
Okay, let's go for now with the possibility that an איסטרי istari
is four זוזא. zuza. Okay, so you know, if you think of,
what would be an example? If you think of a זוז zuz.
as a quarter, you know, in American money, and an איסטרי istari
would be a dollar. So do we consider it to mean six
hundred dollars and a quarter?
שית מאה איסטרי וזוזא. shis mea istari vezuza. או דילמא שית מאה
פריטי וזוזא? o dilma shis mea priti vezuza?
No, maybe the six hundred is six hundred pennies and a זוז.
zuz.
Okay, so you got the two possibilities? We're going to have a
third one in a minute. Okay, it says six
hundred plus one זוז. zuz Okay, so what is that going to
mean? So will that mean like six hundred,
let's say a זוז zuz, is let's say a quarter. Okay, of,
you know, in American money. Are we going to say it means
six hundred dollars plus one quarter? Or are we going to say
it means six hundred pennies
plus one quarter? Okay, those are the two possibilities. Okay, this is
the פריטי priti and this is the איסטרא. istira.
Okay, so got it? So which one? Now there's another possibility. What
else could it mean?
What else could it mean?
Six hundred plus one זוז, zuz. what else could it mean?
What?
שית מאה זוזא וזוזא. shis mea zuza vezuza. What?
שית מאה זוזא וזוזא.
shis mea
zuza
vezuza.
0-0 what?
Meaning, well no, not six thousand and one, that wouldn't be. But
it could just mean six hundred זוזא zuza and one זוזא. zuza.
Who says we're dealing with different coinage? He borrowed from him six
hundred and a זוז. zuz. Six hundred, so maybe it means six
hundred and one זוז. zuz. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא'ס Gemara's but
these are the two possibilities the גמרא is asking. Either a higher
value or
literally what it says, six hundred and one.
שית מאה, shis mea, yeah, but the language was, it
said שית מאה וזוזא. shis mea vezuza. It didn't say שית מאה
וחד זוזא. shis mea vechad zuza. It says six hundred and a
זוז. zuz All right, so anyway, yes, fine. But we're assuming questioning
whether it's an amount more than a זוז zuz. or less than
a זוז. zuz. So let's see what he says. אמר ליה דל
פריטי. amar lei dal priti. No, no, no. Take out the possibility
of פריטי, priti, of pennies. דלא כתיבי בשטרא. delo ketivi beshtara. It
would not have been written in a שטר, pennies. Why not? דאחוכי
מחככי להו. deachochei mechachakei lehu. Because you would just sort of add
them up, meaning you would basically to the higher amount, which doesn't
mean they would never be written in a שטרא shtar at all,
like I might have bought from you a million dollars and twenty
three cents, okay? But in this case, why would I have written
six hundred pennies and a quarter? If I'm using a quarter here
as a coinage, why wouldn't I just say this as forty quarters?
Right? Did I do the math right? No, I didn't do the
math right. Whatever. What? One fifty. One hundred and fifty. Okay, whatever.
No. Yeah? No. Four, no, whatever. Okay, whatever it is.
No, it's twenty-two.
No, twenty-four. Twenty-four times twenty-five is six hundred, right? Oh, I'm
thinking
fifty. Yeah.
Anyway, whatever it be. Why wouldn't I just say twenty-four quarters and
a quarter, right? So if I'm dealing with a higher coinage here,
why would I mention six hundred pennies?
Like just say it in זוז. zuz. So this can't be the
possibility, okay? It would not have been six hundred פרוטות prutos and
a זוז. zuz. I'll take basically, by the way, just so you
know the actual coinage, a פרוטה pruta is about one two-hundredth of
a זוז. zuz So this would have been basically like four and
change, okay? So why not just say five זוז zuz? and change?
Why say six hundred plus a זוז? zuz.
Why does רש"י Rashi say one hundred and ninety-two?
That's what I just said. Roughly two hundred. Oh, okay. I'm just
trying to translate this into American coinage so you more immediately understand
it. But if this was, if this was actually פרוטות, prutos, this
would have been about four זוז. zuz? So who would have said
six hundred פרוטות prutos and a זוז? zuz You would have said
five זוז zuz. and change. Okay, so that can't be the possibility.
So the fact that it means a lesser coinage is not possible,
we would have just summed it up. Okay, so the גמרא says,
so דאסוכי מסכי להו, deasuchei maschei lehu, מסכי להו זוזא. maschei lehu
zuza. You would have just summed it up and translated it into
זוז. zuz. So מאי אמרת? mai amarta? So what should we say?
שש מאה sheish meah אסתרי istari וזוזא, v'zuza, let's say therefore it
means this, six hundred dollars, like six hundred אסתרי, istari, a higher
amount than a זוז. zuz, Okay, that's possible. So, but for now
there are two possibilities. It means six hundred dollars and a זוז,
zuz or it could
mean, we'll read the parentheses, שש מאה sheish meah זוזי zuzei וחד
זוזא. v'chad zuza. Or do we say it means six hundred זוז
zuz? and a זוז? So to choose between these two, so you
guys are trying to figure it out as which is the more
logical, and you think since there's no coinage here we should go
by the coinage mentioned here. That's one way of saying it, but
the גמרא has another way of saying it. אמר אביי יד בעל
השטר על התחתונה. Amar Abaye yad baal hashtar al hatochtuna. So the
גמרא says forget the question of which is more logical. Maybe we
can't figure out which is more logical, but we're going to interpret
it as the lesser amount. And this is a lesser amount because
the אסתרי istari is a higher coinage. Okay, so this would really
be the lesser amount, but we don't say יד בעל השטר על
התחתונה to say an absurd thing. So you would never have said
six hundred pennies and a quarter. You would have summed them up
into a larger, you know, into a larger coinage. So we eliminate
this as a possibility, and within these two, we pick the lesser
amount, יד בעל השטר על התחתונה.
Exactly, it's exactly what it's saying. Okay, so this is where we
will end for today.
Just the סוף. sof.